<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


1) A poem composed by a Lady of the Court upon the death of Emperor Tenji   (her name is unknown)

生身の人間である私は神の力（ちから） には逆らえず、君から離（はな） されて、朝にも君を慕い嘆き、遠く君に恋い焦がれる。もしもあなたが玉であったなら、手に巻き付けて持ち、着物だとしたら脱ぐときもない。それほど私が恋い慕う君が、昨夜の夢に現（あらわ） れました。
As a flesh-and-blood person, I am powerless against the will of the gods. Separated from you, I grieve for you in the morning. Kept away, I yearn for you. If you were a jewel, I would wrap you round my wrist. If you were a robe, I would never take you off. Lord whom I long for so much, last night I saw you in my dream.



2) A poem of self-lamentation by a Monk of the Gango-ji Temple


（海底（かいてい）にあって人に知られない）真珠のような私の博識（はくしき）は人に知られない。　だが、世（よ）の人が知らなくてもよい。　人が知らなくても、私自身（わたしじしん）が知っていたなら、他人（たにん）なんか知らなくてもかまわない。
(My true worth that is comparable to) a pearl (resting at the bottom of the sea) is not known to others. But, it doesn't matter if others don't know it. Even if they don't, if I myself know my true worth, it doesn't matter if the world doesn't recognize it.


3) A poem on the moon (Anonymous)
春日山を一面に照らしているこの月は、いとしい人の庭にもさやかに照っていたことだなあ。
The moon that now bathes the whole of Mount Kasuga also shone brightly on my sweet love's garden!


4) A poem on clouds (from the Hitomaro Collection)
谷間の瀬の音の響きが激しくなるにつれて、弓月が岳一面に雲が立ち昇ってゆく。
As the sound of the mountain rapids roars and reverberates, clouds rise and hover over Yutsuki Peak.


5) A poem on a Japanese zither   　(Anonymous)
琴を手に取ると、まず嘆きが先に立つ。　ひょっとしたら、この琴の胴の中に妻がひそんでいるのではなかろうか。
Grief takes over me as soon as I take the zither in my hand. Can it be that in the body of the zither my wife is lurking?

6) 
Anonymous
ほとばしり落ちて流れる水が岩にさえぎられて淀んでいる岩かげに、月の影が映ってみえることよ。
In the backwater formed by the rocks blocking the tumbling torrents, I see the image of the moon.


7) A spring poem from the "Hitomaro Collection"
天の香具山にこよいは霞がたなびいている。　春がきたらしいな。
A mist is hanging over heavenly Kasuga Hill. Spring must be upon us!

8) A spring poem from the "Hitomaro Collection"
こんなに恋しいものだと知っていたら、夕方におりて朝には消える露であったら、と願っただろうに。
If I had known that my love sickness was to be so painful, I would have wished that I were the dew that forms in the evening and vanishes in the morning.


9) A poem from Hitachi Province

筑波山に雪が降ったのだろうか？　いや、そうではなくて、いとしいあの子が布を干したのだろうか？　
Has snow fallen on Mt. Tsukuba? Or rather, has my darling girl hung out cloth to dry?


10) Azuma Uta (Eastland Poems):　A poem from Musashi Province

多摩川に（さらさらと）晒（さら）す手織りの布ではないが、どうしてあの子がこんなにひどく（さらにさらに）可愛いのだろうか。
Like the rustling ("sarasara") of the homespun cloth set out to bleach ("sarasu") in the Tama River, why do I think so tenderly of that darling girl more and yet more ("sarasara ni")?



11) Azuma Uta (Eastland Poems):　A poem from Shinano Provin
信濃にある千曲川の小石でも、あなたが踏んだものならば、玉と思って拾いましょう。
Even the pebbles on the beach of the Chikuma River in Shinano, if stepped on by you, I will gather them as precious stones.



12) Azuma Uta (Eastland Poems):　A "love song"
稲を搗くのであかぎれが切れている私の手を、今夜もまた、お屋敷の若様は手にとって嘆かれることだろうか。
Will the young son of the lord of the manor, tonight again, hold my hands hardened and chapped from hilling the rice, and sigh?



13)      Poems exchanged between the members of the Embassy to Silla of 736 and those who were left at home, and poems on the afflictions and and sorrows of the voyage.



あなたが行く途中の海辺の宿に霧が立ったなら、私がここで嘆いているそのため息だと思ってください。
If a mist should rise on your way where you lodge by the sea, please know it is my breath as I sigh standing here.


14) Anonymous
私のために妻が嘆いているらしい。　風速の浦の沖のあたりに、霧がたなびいているよ。
My wife must be sighing after me. Some way out at sea from the shore of Kazayaha, a mist is trailing.


15) A lament composed by an anonymous member of the embassy for another member who died en route to Korea.
世の中というものは、いつもこのようでしかないものとばかりに死んでいったあなたに、ただわけもなく恋い焦がれながら、私は旅を続けてゆくのだろうか。
Am I to go on, continuing this journey, senselessly longing for you who has departed from us as if meaning to say that the way of the world has always been like this?


16) By a frontier-guard's wife
防人に行くのは誰の夫かと聞いている人を見るのは羨ましいことよ。　何も思い煩うこともなしに。
How I envy seeing a woman asking who is going as a frontier-guard.　 So free from all anxieties!










