<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

Yamanoe Okura


この憶良はもう退出しましょう。　子どもが泣いているでしょう。　それにその子の母親も私を待っているでしょうに。 　
I, Okura, must take my leave of you now.　 My children may be crying.　 And yes, their mother, too, may be waiting for me.






瓜を食べると子供のことが思われる。栗を食べると、いっそう子供が偲ばれる。（いったい）子供はどこから（どのような縁（えん）で、私のところに）来たものだろうか。　目の前にちらついて、私を安眠させない。
When I eat melons, I think of my children. When I eat chestnuts, I miss them even more. By what turn of fate did they come to me? Flickering before my eyes incessantly, they would not let me sleep in peace.





銀も金も宝石も、何の役に立とうか。　（それらよりも）すぐれた宝である子に及ぶことがあろうか。　
What good to me are gold, silver, or jewels? How could they equal a child that is the greater treasure?


風まじりの雨が降り、雨にまじって雪が降る夜（よる）は 
On the night when rain falls driven by the wind, when snow falls mingled with the rain
どうしようもなく寒いので、堅塩（かたしお）を取（と）って少（すこ）しずつかじり 
Feeling helplessly cold, I take a lump of hard-baked salt and nibble on it
糟湯酒（かすゆざけ）を啜（すす）りながら、咳（せき）をし、鼻をぐずぐずと鳴（な）らし 
While I sip sake lees diluted in hot water, I cough and sniffle with a running nose
みすぼらしい髭（ひげ）を掻（か）き撫（な）でて、自分以外（じぶんいがい）にたいした人物（じんぶつ）はいまいと自負（じふ）してみても
Stroking my scanty beard, I say in my pride "There's none greater than I!"
やはり寒（さむ）いので、麻（あさ）の夜具（やぐ）を引（ひ）きかぶり 
But I am still cold, and so I pull up my hempen bedclothes around my shoulders
布（ぬの）の肩掛（かたか）けをありったけ重（かさ）ねて着（き）ても寒い夜（よる）でさえあるのに 
And, though I put on every sleeveness jacket I have, the night is still cold
私よりも貧しい人の父母は飢（う）えて凍（こご）えていることだろう 
As for the man poorer than I am, his father and mother must be starving and growing numb with cold
妻（つま）や子供（こども）たちは、食べ物（たべもの）をせがんで泣（な）いていることだろう 
His wife and children must be begging for food and crying
こんな時（とき）は、どのようにしてお前（まえ）はこの世（よ）を過（す）ごしているのか 
At times like these, how do you manage to get through your life?
天地（てんち）は広（ひろ）いというのに、私のためには狭（せま）くなったのだろうか 
Although they say that the heaven and earth are vast, have they become cramped for me?
太陽（たいよう）や月（つき）は明（あか）るいというけれど、私のためには照（て）ってくださらないのだろうか 
Although they say that the sun and moon are bright, do they not favor me with their light?
人は皆（みな）こうなのか、それとも私だけがこうなのだろうか
Is it the same with all men, or thus for me alone?
たまたま人間（にんげん）として生（う）まれ、ひとなみに私も働（はたら）いているのに 
By rare chance I was born a man, and as any man I toil to make a living on the land
綿（わた）も入（は）っていない粗末（そまつ）な袖無（そでな）しの、海藻（かいそう）のようにやぶれて垂（た）れ下（さ）がっているぼろばかりを肩（かた）にかけて 
Wearing only tattered clothes, an unpadded sleeveless hemp jacket hanging from my shoulders like seaweeds
低（ひく）くてみすぼらしくゆがんで傾（かたむ）いた家（いえ）の中（なか）に、地（じ）べたに藁（わら）をばらばらに敷（し）いて 
And in this dingy low-roofed hut, this crooked hut with leaning walls, I lie on straw spread on bare ground
父母は枕の方に、妻（つま）や子（こ）どもは足（あし）の方（ほう）に、自分（じぶん）を囲（かこ）んでいて 嘆（なげ）いたり呻（うめ）いたりしており
With my parents near my pillow, and my wife and children at my feet, huddled together bewailing and moaning
かまどには煙（けむり）もたてず、米蒸し器（こめむしき）には蜘蛛（くも）の巣（す）がかかって 
No smoke rises from the cooking stove, and in the pot a spider spins its web.
飯（めし）を炊（た）くことも忘（わす）れて、呻き声（うめきごえ）を出（だ）しているのに 
While we moan and groan oblivious even of the very way of cooking rice
「極端（きょくたん）に短（みじか）いものの端（はし）をさらに切（き）る」という諺（ことわざ）のように 
"To cut the end off of what is already very short," as the saying goes,
鞭（むち）を持（も）った村長（そんちょう）の声（こえ）が寝屋（ねや）のところまで来（き）て呼（よ）び立（た）ている
There comes the voice of the whip-brandishing village headman, shouting for me, standing outside the place where we sleep.
これほどどうにもならないものだろうか、この世の中（よのなか）を生（い）きてゆく道（みち）というものは
Is it really this hopeless, the path of a man's life in this world?






この世の中を身も細（ほそ）るようにつらく思うけれども、飛び立つこともできない。　鳥ではないのだから。
Though I may think this world is depressing and unbearable, I cannot simply fly away from it for I am not a bird.




男子たるものが空しく朽ち果ててよいものだろうか。　いつの世までも語り継ぐに足る名声も立てないで。
Should anyone who calls himself a man idle his time away and die in obscurity, without having established a renown that should live on people's lips for all ages?


秋の野に咲いている花を指を折って数えてみると、七種類の花がある。
When I count on my fingers the flowers that bloom in the autumn fields, I find there are seven.



